<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<projects>
    <section name="Bio-Materials">
        <project name="BIO-INDUSTRIAL MATERIALS INSTITUTE">
            <summary>
                The success of bast plants (e.g., hemp, jute, kenaf, flax) in industrial and technical applications is 
                completely a function of how they compare to other plant-based and synthetic materials on a cost and performance basis. 
                The Center for Bio-industrial Materials Institute (BMI) has the mission of collaboratively establishing a 
                comprehensive understanding of bio-industrial materials from bast plants (both hurd and fiber), their opportunities, and 
                how to economically process them into useful products, through partnerships to increase their competitiveness and material use.  
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                  Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, SUNY New Paltz, Innotech International LLC, PureHempNY, NY HempLab
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Hemp (492 x4 02).jpg" alt="Ten Char of Sus Mtl"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="TENSILE CHARACTERIZATION OF BIO-POLYMERS AND BIO-COMPOSITES">
            <summary>
                Bio-Polymer (skeletal mycelium) has the potential of replacing petroleum based foams in many applications.  This material is extremely complient which
                makes the experimental evaluation of its tensile properties challenging.  Strength, elastic modulus, and Poisson's ration need to be characterized for
                these materials in bulk form.  A tensile test method had to be developed that would allow the material to be properly characterized.  The full field strain technique DIC
                was employed to validate the method and collect deformation data.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                  Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Ecovative Design LLC, Innotech International LLC, National Science Foundation (NSF), New York State Energy Research and Development Authority (NYSERDA)
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Ten Char of Sus Mtl (500 x 317).jpg" alt="Ten Char of Sus Mtl"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="COMPRESSIVE CHARACTERIZATION OF BIO-POLYMERS AND BIO-COMPOSITES">
            <summary>
                Bio-Polymer (skeletal mycelium) has the potential of replacing petroleum based foams in many applications.  This material is extremely complient which
                makes the experimental evaluation of its compressive properties challenging.  Strength, elastic modulus, and Poisson's ration need to be characterized for
                these materials in bulk form.  A compressive test method had to be developed that would allow these material to be properly characterized. The full field strain technique DIC
                was employed to validate the method and collect deformation data.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Ecovative Design LLC, Innotech International LLC, National Science Foundation (NSF), New York State Energy Research and Development Authority (NYSERDA)
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - BioPolymer Compression (500 x 260).jpg" alt="Comp Char of Sus Mtl"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="ENGINEERED WOOD DEVELOPMENT USING BIO-POLYMERS">
            <summary>
                Bio-Polymer (skeletal mycelium) has the potential of replacing petroleum based glues in engineered wood applications.  Material characterization testing
                is used to optimize the manufacturing parameters associated with production of engineered woods using bio-polymer
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Ecovative Design LLC, Innotech International LLC, National Science Foundation (NSF), New York State Energy Research and Development Authority (NYSERDA)
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Janka Ball Testing (200 x 133).jpg" alt="Char of Sus Engineered Wood"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="DEVELOPING BIOCOMPOSITES FOR ENGINEERING APPLICATIONS">
            <summary>
                The development of sustainable materials for engineering applications is an ongoing, collaborative, effort.  The goal is to replace petroleum based foams 
                and plastics with the use of sustainable materials.  For this effort to be successful, the sustainable alternative materials must perform as well as or better than their 
                petroleum counterparts.  This project is supporting local industry in the development and characterization of these materials.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Ecovative Design LLC, Innotech International LLC, National Science Foundation (NSF), New York State Energy Research and Development Authority (NYSERDA)
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - BioComposite Applications (500 x 223).jpg" alt="Eng Applic for BioComposites"></image>
        </project>
    </section>

    <section name="Bio-Mechanics">
    
        <project name="MECHANICAL TESTING OF MUSCULOSKELETAL TISSUE">
            <summary>
                The mechanical behavior of rabbit Medial Collateral Ligaments (MCL)to various treatments is being studied in vitro. Treatments were
                performed to the rabbit MCL's, harvested by a veterinarian, and tissue not vital to the evaluation were removed.  Specialty test fixtures 
                were fabricated to insure the load was placed axially on the ligament.  Each specimen was imaged in a micro-CT to evaluate 
                the cross-sectional area of the MCL.  The Digital Image Correlation technique was used to evaluate strains on the surface of the ligament.  
                Standard test procedures were used to preform the evaluations.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                OrthoGraph, Innotech International LLC, Albany Medical College
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - MCL (500 x 224).jpg" alt="MCL Testing"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="EVALUATING ANTERIOR CRUCIATE LIGAMENT TEARS DUE TO ATHLETIC SURFACES AND FOOTWARE">
            <summary>
                Today, Anterior Cruciate Ligament (ACL) tears are one of the most prevalent knee injuries, with the occurrence of 
                ACL tears increasing drastically from approximately 80 000 in 2000 to 150 000 in 2011. Although there are many factors that 
                contribute to an ACL tear occurring, certain environmental factors could contribute to the dramatic increase over the past couple 
                decades, especially in athletes. This study explores two of these possible factors; the playing surface and the type of shoes worn 
                by soccer players. The effects these factors have on ACL tears were evaluated by measuring the maximum torque achieved prior to the 
                shoe breaking free of the playing surface using a servo-hydraulic bi-axial load frame.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Albany Medical College, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - ACL (500 x 234 ).jpg" alt="ACL Testing"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="OPTIMIZING POROUS BONE CONSTRUCT USING ADDITIVE MANUFACTURING">
            <summary>
                Patient specific implants are becoming viable treatment options in some orthopaedic applications through advances in additive 
                manufacturing and 3D printing techniques. One potential application is for treatment of segmental bone defects, particularly in patients 
                suffering from bone cancer. Current treatment options are: Amputation, megaprosthesis, or allografts. These treatments are often highly 
                invasive, may require a partial/full joint replacement and are limited by mechanical properties, which affect the life of the implant. 
                The Ti6Al4V implant proposed in this research was designed to fit a mid-diaphyseal segmental bone defect, mimic the mechanical properties of bone, 
                facilitate osseointegration and reduce wear at the bone-implant surface. 
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                ReVivo, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Femur (500 x 154).jpg" alt="Eval of Porous Bone Construct"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="MEASURING DEFORMATIONS ON THE SURFACE OF A HEART">
            <summary>
                 Many techniques used to measure the deformation of biological tissue are inadequate for measuring deformations of hearts in vivo. Bull Frogs (Rana Catesbeiana) 
                were double-pithed and dissected to expose the amphibian heart for the measurements conducted in this study. White titanium dioxide powder and black charcoal 
                were applied to the surface of the heart to create an artificial surface pattern with high contrast that does not react with the heart muscle or mask surface 
                details. This pattern was then used in conjunction with three dimensional Digital Image Correlation (DIC) to measure full field deformations of the heart 
                through several cardiac cycles. These deformations were measured with a spatial resolution of approximately 0.4 m and temporal resolution of 50 Hz
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Stony Brook University, Union College Biology Department
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Projects - Frog Hearts (500 x 231).jpg" alt="DIC on Hearts"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="EVALUATION OF INTERVERTEBRAL DISC DEGENERATION AND RECOVERY">
            <summary>
                Lower back pain is a disorder that is experienced by millions every year.  This condition is often attributed to damage of the 
                intervertebral disc annulus fibrosus.  This project is studying several therapeutic methodologies to mitigate this condition or regenerate the 
                intervertebral disc.  Spinal segments are studied experimentally in vitro.   Animal and cadaver specimens are subjected to specific testing 
                protocols to evaluate the performance of the discs.  The use of the Digital Image Correlation Technique is invaluable in developing the understanding 
                of the load paths in the spinal segments.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Albany Medical College, Innotech International LLC, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Spine (500 x 125 ).jpg" alt="Intervertebral Disc Evaluation"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="MEASURING DEFORMATIONS ON COLOBINE MANDIBULAR SYMPHYSIS">
            <summary>
                The masticatory loading regime of lateral transverse bending (wishboning)is hypothesized to be instrumental in the evolution of symphyseal form
                among primates. The biomechanics of wishboning have largely been inferred by assuming that the mandible behaves as a curved beam under 
                this load; however, the characterization of stress and strain in the anthropoid symphysis has been interpretively challenging. This is due, in part, 
                to both limitations of sampling strain in an in vivo context and the incongruence of beam theory assumptions on the one hand, and the anatomical 
                complexity of mandibular morphology on the other. Utilizing three-dimensional (3D) Digital Image Correlation (DIC), we employ an in vitro 
                approach to characterize the strain field in a sample of colobine mandibles under simulated wishboning loads in order to assess the utility of 
                idealized curved beam models for characterizing strain gradients in symphyseal bone. 
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                University of Florida, Ohio State University
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Mandible (500 x 173).jpg" alt="DIC on Colobine Mandibular Symphysis"></image>
        </project>
    </section>

    <section name="Advanced Materials">

        <project name="ISOGRID DEVELOPMENT">
            <summary>
                Isogrid structures are made up of a lattice or ribs oriented in an equilateral configuration that give the structure isotropic characteristics.  
                Metallic isogrids were found to be extremely efficient (load bearing capability with respect to weight); however, very costly to manufacture.  
                Isogrid structures fabricated from composite materials were able to take advantage of the extreme anisotropy of continuous carbon fibers to increase 
                structural efficiency well above metallic isogrids.  Most of the applications the successfully used composite isogrids were filament wound and took 
                advantage of winding tension to flatten the fiber tows at intersections that allowed deleterious build-up in thickness to be avoided.  Because of the 
                use of the need for winding tension, flat composite isogrids were found to be extremely difficult and impractical to produce using filament winding 
                techniques.  This study explores the production of flat composite isogrids that eliminates build-ups at intersections, does not rely on winding tension, 
                and maintains the advantageous structural efficiency of isogrids.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                U.S. Air Force, NASA, Automated Dynamics, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - IsoGrids (500 x 348).jpg" alt="Composite Isogrid Dev"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="COMPOSITE MATERIAL CHARACTERIZATION USING STANDARD METHODS">
            <summary>
                The performance of composite materials is dependent on the constituent materials (fiber, matrix, sizing), the proportions of the constituents
                (volume fractions), component geometry, and the method used to manufacture the component.  The sensitivity of composite materials to these factors make standard
                characterization methods essential to modeling efforts.  The Mechanics Lab has performed most of the ASTM test standards related to composite characterization.  
                The lab has also developed specialized test methods for characterizing the performance of composite structures.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                U.S. Navy, U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force, NASA, Automated Dynamics, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Advanced Material Characterization (500 x 211).jpg" alt="Composite Stand Characterization"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="COMPOSITE MATERIAL STRUCTURAL DESIGN">
            <summary>
                One of the most important issues in composite material design is joining composite structures to other materials.  Conventional joint of 
                fasteners can at best yield a joint that is 40 percent efficient.  Bonded and fastened joints also have to account for significant differences in thermal 
                expansion coefficients that give rise to high residual stresses if the structure is subjected to temperature variations.  The Composite Material and Mechanics 
                Labs have been involved in several structural development efforts that involve the modeling and experimental evaluation of composite structures 
                that are being designed for hostile environments.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                NASA, Automated Dynamics, Cameron, FMC Technologies, StatOil, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Advanced Composite Design (500 x 242).jpg" alt="Composite Structural Design"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="SECOND GENERATION HIGH TEMPERATURE SUPERCONDUCTING WIRE DEVELOPMENT">
            <summary>
                Second Generation (2G) High Temperature Superconductors (HTS) become superconducting at high temperatures (liquid nitrogen).  This generation
                of wire is a significant improvement over first generation wire that need more costly and colder liquid helium to become superconducting.  This generation of
                HTS wire improves capacity per cross-sectional area, improves reliability and quality of power, increases efficiency in transmission of power, reduces operating 
                costs, and has significant environmental benefits over 1G HTs and conventional wire.  The mechanics lab	supported the development of 2G HTS by developing a cross 
                tension test procedure to evaluate the quality of the 2G HTS wire at both room and liquid nitrogen temperatures
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Super Power Inc, New York State
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - HT Super Conducting Wire (500 x 204).jpg" alt="2G HTS Wire Dev"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="COMPOSITE MATERIALS FOR INFRASTRUCTURE APPLICATIONS">
            <summary>
                Composite materials are being used in infrastructure projects for repair, increase the capacity of older structures, and design more structurally efficient 
                new structures.  The Composite Materials Manufacturing Lab and the Mechanics Lab have been involved in several project related to infrastructure.  These projects 
                include test method development, material screening, design, and professional development.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                New York State Department of Transportation, Federal Highway Administration, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Composites in Infrastructure (500 x 142).jpg" alt="Infrastructure App of Comp MTL"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="AEROGEL PROCESS DEVELOPMENT">
            <summary>
                The development of the fabrication process of aerogel monoliths using a hot press was pioneered in the Composite Materials Manufacturing 
                lab at Union College.  This process significantly reduced the fabrication time, while maintaining the unique characteristics of aerogels.  Characterizations 
                efforts were initially carried out in the Mechanics Lab at Union College.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                New York State Department of Transportation, Federal Highway Administration, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Aerogels (500 x 153).jpg" alt="Aerogel Dev"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="SINGLE FIBER CHARACTERIZATION">
            <summary>
                The experimental characterization of single fibers (carbon, glass, etc) are evaluated using tensile stage.  A specialized tensile stage was designed
                and constructed in the Mechanics Lab to fit under the optical microscope.  This additional stage gives the lab the capability to study dry fiber and fiber embedded
                in a surrounding matrix material.  Dry fiber strength, dry fiber modulus, and the strength of the fiber-matrix interface have been successfully evaluated in the 
                Mechanics Lab using these stages.  The method for testing single dry fibers was developed by the lab.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Vital Materials 
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Single Fiber Testing (500 x 134).jpg" alt="Single Fiber Characterization"></image>
        </project>
    </section>

    <section name="Fatigue &amp; Fracture">

        <project name="FATIGUE EVALUATION OF CLOSED CROSS-SECTIONED COMPOSITES">
            <summary>
                In traditional homogenous materials, failure results from the propagation of a single crack. In composite materials cracks (both 
                inter-laminar matrix cracking, intra-laminar matrix cracking, and fiber breaks) form throughout the material during its life cycle and failure 
                results from the accumulation of these various types of damage.  This process is dependent on fiber architecture, materials used, and structural 
                geometry.  A thorough understanding of damage accumulation is critical to structural assessment.  Traditional characterization of laminated composite 
                materials occurs on flat coupons.  The free edges of the flat laminated composite coupons give rise to an exacerbated interlaminar state of stress 
                that dominate the formation of damage.  Many composite structures are of a closed form configuration that do not have free-edges.  Traditional 
                coupons do not accurately characterize the performance of closed form laminated structures.   For this reason a new specimen configuration and test 
                procedure was developed to study the accumulation of damage in closed cross-section composite structures under static and fatigue loading.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Fatigue (500 x 408).jpg" alt="Fatigue in Closed X-Section Composites"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="EXPERIMENTALLY DETERMINED J-INTEGRAL IN DCDC SPECIMENS">
            <summary>
                In fracture mechanics the formation and propagation of cracks in brittle solids are studied using the Double Cleavage Drilled 
                Compression (DCDC).  Glass DCDC specimens with various hole configurations were studied using the Digital Image Correlation (DIC) technique.  
                This technique enabled the strain field around to be measured.  These strains were then used to numerically compute the stress-intensity factor 
                at the crack tip using the J-Integral technique.
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
                U.S. Air Force, U.S. Army, NASA, Innotech International LLC
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - DCDC (500 x 217 ).jpg" alt="Fatigue in Closed X-Section Composites"></image>
        </project>

    </section>

    <section name="Miscellaneous Projects">

        <project name="STUDENT COMPETITIONS">
            <summary>
                Student competitions give students the opportunity to apply concepts learned in the classroom to the design, construction, and evaluation 
                of engineering challenges.  Student competitions also give student exposure to potential employers and an opportunity to start building their professional 
                network. Many of these projects have taken advantage of the resources available in the Composite Manufacturing and Mechanics labs.  These 
                competitions include ASME Human Powered Vehicle, SAE Formula, SAE Air Cargo, SAMPE Student Bridge Competition, and several others.
            </summary>
            <collaborators></collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Student Competitions (500 x 308).jpg" alt="Student Competitions"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="STUDENT MOTIVTED PROJECTS">
            <summary>
                The Composite Manufacturing and Mechanics labs include spaces for student innovation and have a long history of supporting student innovation.  
                Some students come to college with a deep passion, develop an interest through their studies, or are just curious enough about a particular topic that a project develops. 
                These are the seeds of future innovation and the student innovation spaces help students develop the confidence that will lead to a career of innovation.  Student 
                motivated projects include development of a torsional load cell, a six-degree-of-freedom load platform, a tensile stage for a microscope, a electro-magnetic 
                actuated load frame for studying spinal segments, an innovative integrated bike frame and suspension, an adjustable sled hockey frame, and an adjustable prosthetic. 
            </summary>
            <collaborators>
            
            </collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Project - Student Motivated (500 x 279).jpg" alt="Student Motivated Projects"></image>
        </project>

        <project name="INTERNATIONAL STUDENT PROJECTS">
            <summary>
                Engineering has evolved into a global enterprise where projects routinely involve international collaborators. To help prepare students for the 
                internationalization of engineering, several programs were created to give Union College engineering students international engineering project experiences.  
                The International Virtual Design Studio (IVDS) project is a collaboration with the Middle East Technical University in Ankara, Turkey; Altim University in Ankara, 
                Turkey; and ESIGELEC in Rouen, France.  IVDS teams Union College engineering students with international students to remotely work on a project as a team.  IVDS typically 
                runs between six and nine months and includes a visit to the US by the international students and a visit to the collaborating institution by the Union College students.  
                Additionally, Union College has chapters of Engineers Without Borders (EWB) and Engineers for a Sustainable World (ESW) which have led to international design projects to 
                sustainability support communities in the developing world.   
            </summary>
            <collaborators></collaborators>
            <image url="content/data/labs/Projects - International Projects (500 x 278).jpg" alt="Student Motivated Projects"></image>
        </project>
    </section>
	
</projects>